A Finding Aid to the Buell Mullen Papers, 1942-1982, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Buell Mullen papers
1942-1982
Archives of American Art
Mullen, Buell (1901-1986)
AAA.mullbuel
Archival Resource Key
0.4 Linear feet
The papers of muralist Buell Mullen measure 0.4 linear feet and date from 1942 to 1982. Found are scattered biographical material, professional correspondence, information on mixing epoxy resins, printed material, and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Scope and Contents
The papers of muralist Buell Mullen measure 0.4 linear feet and date from 1942 to 1982. Found are scattered biographical material, professional correspondence, information on mixing epoxy resins, printed material, and photographs.
Biographical / Historical
Buell Mullen (1901-1986) was a muralist and portrait painter active in New York City and Chicago, Illinois. She developed a process for painting on stainless steel.
Buell Mullen was born Frances Vedder Buell in Chicago, Illinois. Drawn to its ability to reflect light, Mullen developed a technique combining etching and acid treatments to ensure oil paintings adhere to stainless steel. Her first work on stainless steel was a portrait of General John J. Pershing. Later, she produced a portrait of President Dwight Eisenhower. She completed many murals for steel companies, colleges, and institutions around the Great Lakes region. Also, she served as a United States representative to UNESCO.
Buell married J. Bernard Mullen and together they had two sons. Mullen died in Chicago, Illinois in 1986.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection the papers are arranged as one series.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Buell Mullen donated her papers to the Archives of American Art in 1982.
Muralists -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Portrait painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Women artists; Women painters; Women muralists
- Buell Mullen papers, 1942-1982; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical materials include a resume and an honorary degree from Lake Erie College in Painsville, Ohio. Largely, correspondence concerns Mullen's murals. Letters are from Bowling Green State University, Milton Eisenhower, General Motors, International Minerals and Chemicals Corporation, Johns Hopkins University, Lake Erie College, Dean Rusk, Simon Fraser University, UNESCO, and Urban Coalition. Printed materials consist of published articles by Mullen concerning the process of painting on metal, clippings, mural dedication invitations, and scattered reproductions of works of art. Photographs are of Mullen at work, with her artwork, and presenting her finished works. Also found are photographs of her murals and smaller works of art.
  - Honorary Degree, Lake Erie College, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Resume, circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Epoxy Mixing Technique, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1956-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Articles, by Buell Mullen, 1950s-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1940s-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Mural Dedication Invitations and Brochures, 1942-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Program, 150th Anniversary Ball of the Seventh Regiment of New York, 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Reproductions of Works of Art, circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, of Buell Mullen, 1940s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, of Murals and Works of Art, 1940s-circa 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Slides, 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)